Marcos Alves Cunha

Vancouver, Canada - (Permanent Resident)
alvesfc@protonmail.com
(587) 439-7182

www.linkedin.com/in/alvesfc www.marcosalves.dev

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I have over ten years of experience as a Software Developer specializing in **finance**, **telecom**, and **e-commerce** solutions. My skills include **Java**, **Kotlin**, **JavaScript**, **React**, **TDD** and **BDD**. I have extensive experience in managing databases such as **PostgreSQL**, **MongoDB**, **DynamoDB**, and **Redis**. I also have experience working with **Apache Kafka** for real-time data processing. Additionally, I have expertise in **cloud** solutions, including **AWS** and **GCP**.

EDUCATION

2015 **Specialization in Solutions Architecture**, FIAP 2011 **Bachelor in Information Systems**, Centro Universitário Fundação Santo André

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer, Craver, Vancouver, Canada

July 2023 - Feb 2024

Maintained a legacy system and designed a new POS integration to handle orders and inventories. The project involved creating new features to integrate restaurant menus from platforms like Toast and Square with the Craver platform. Additionally, I took part in an on-call rotation with the tech support team to fix bugs and ensure **system reliability**. The tech stack included **Java 11**, **Spring Boot**, **MySQL**, **Gradle**, **Kubernetes**, and **Google Cloud**.

Senior Software Engineer, Letus, Vancouver, Canada

Dec 2021 - May 2023

Designed and implemented an **SMS notification** service to remind customers about upcoming payments and request authorization to process payments via text messages. I also developed a complete workflow management system consisting of a **messaging template** and a **short URL** system for efficient link handling. The tech stack included **Java 11**, **Spring Boot**, **MongoDB**, **Gradle** and **AWS** services such as **SQS**, **SNS**, and **ECS**.

Senior Software Engineer, PagBank, São Paulo, Brazil

Feb 2020 - Jan 2022

Migrated a critical **Card Tokenization** system to a **microservice architecture**. It securely tokenized credit and debit card data with **low latency**, processing over **800 requests** per second to ensure strict **PCI** compliance. My responsibilities included defining rigorous testing and delivery processes and using **Blue-Green** and **Canary deployment** strategies. The tech stack included **Kotlin**, **Spring Boot**, **Apache Kafka**, **Docker** and **AWS** services like **DynamoDB**, **KMS**, and **ECS**.

Designed and developed a system to facilitate the payment of government benefits. This project involved creating a new authentication mechanism using **OAuth2**, enabling a partner company to authenticate using the client credentials flow with our system. The tech stack included **Kotlin**, **Spring Boot**, **Docker** and **AWS** services like **API Gateway**, **RDS** and **ECS**.

Marcos Cunha July 2024

Sabbatical Break Canada & USA Jun 2019 - Feb 2020

I explored cities across Canada and the USA to improve my English and expand my personal and professional horizons.

Tech Lead Gympass, São Paulo, São Paulo *Jan 2019 - May 2019*

Developed a billing solution that integrated with the payroll system. This project included building an integration to retrieve data via **FTP** and process it within our billing system. The tech stack included **Scala** and **Akka**, **Kubernetes**.

Senior Software Engineer, PagBank, São Paulo, Brazil Set 2014 - Jan 2019

Architected and implemented a billing system that efficiently processed thousands of daily charges and integrated with an existing legacy system using a microservices architecture. The tech stack included Java 8, Spring Boot, Docker, Apache Cassandra, Apache Spark, and Apache Mesos.

Constructed a custom **Gradle plugin** to automate the configuration and deployment of **microservices**. Also, a **Jenkins** pipeline was set up, reducing the time needed to deploy applications to production by 80%.

Developed a robust test architecture for microservices using **Spring Cloud Contract**, **Docker**, **Localstack**, **Jenkins**, and **Sonar** while implementing **TDD** and **BDD** methodologies. This significantly improved the quality and frequency of production deliveries. I also enhanced the **Java-based** legacy system by creating **unit tests**, removing **redundant code**, and increasing **test coverage**.

PREVIOUS EXPERIENCES

Senior Software Engineer, <u>Via Varejo SA</u> - Sep/2012 - Sep/2014- São Paulo, Brazil Java Developer, <u>Indra Politec</u> - Feb/2012 - Sep/2012 - São Paulo, Brazil Java Developer, <u>Prodesp</u> - January/2011 - Feb/2012 - São Paulo, Brazil Java Developer, <u>Atento</u> - Jan/2010 - Jan/2011 - São Paulo, Brazil Intern, <u>Excelência Soluções</u> - Jul/2008 - Dec/2010 - São Paulo, Brazil

CERTIFICATES

2019 **English General**, Oxford International / Eurocentres Toronto-San Diego-Vancouver 2018 **Developing on AWS**, AWS Training and Certification 2018 **Architecting on AWS**, AWS Training and Certification

TECHNICAL SKILLS

(10+ years): Java, Spring, Linux, Git, Junit.

(6+ years): OracleDB, PostgreSQL, MySql, Gradle, Jenkins, Docker, Contract testing, TDD, BDD, Splunk.

(3+ years): DynamoDB, KMS, EC2, Oauth2, Apache Kafka, Groovy, New Relic, Gatling, Kotlin, Cucumber, OpenAPI, Kubernetes, DevOps.

(1 year): React, JavaScript, NodeJS

Marcos Cunha July 2024